<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: integer programming | Spaghetti Optimization]]></title>
  <link href="http://stegua.github.io/blog/categories/integer-programming/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://stegua.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-27T12:56:54+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://stegua.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Stefano Gualandi]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[From blackboard to code: Gomory Cuts using CPLEX]]></title>
    <link href="http://stegua.github.io/blog/2013/02/05/gomory-cuts-with-cplex/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-05T15:22:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://stegua.github.io/blog/2013/02/05/gomory-cuts-with-cplex</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Edited on May 16th, 2013</strong>: fixes due to <a href="http://imada.sdu.dk/~marco/">M. Chiarandini</a></p>

<p>On the blackboard, to solve small Integer Linear Programs with 2 variables and <em>less or equal</em> constraints is easy,
since they can be plotted in the plane and the linear relaxation can be solved geometrically. 
You can draw the lattice of integer points, and once you have found a new cutting plane, 
you show that it <em>cuts off</em> the optimum solution of the LP relaxation.</p>

<p>This post presents a naive (textbook) implementation of <strong>Fractional Gomory Cuts</strong> that uses the basic solution
computed by CPLEX, the commercial Linear Programming solver used in our lab sessions.
In practice, this post is an online supplement to one of my last exercise session.</p>

<p>In order to solve the <em>“blackboard”</em> examples with <a href="http://www-01.ibm.com/software/integration/optimization/cplex-optimizer/">CPLEX</a>,
it is necessary to use a couple of functions
that a few years ago were undocumented. <a href="http://www.gurobi.com">GUROBI</a> has very similar functions,
but they are currently undocumented. (<strong>Edited May 16th, 2013</strong>: From version 5.5, Gurobi has documented its 
<a href="http://www.gurobi.com/documentation/5.5/reference-manual/node109">advanced simplex routines</a>)</p>

<p>As usual, all the sources used to write this post are publicly available on 
<a href="https://github.com/stegua/MyBlogEntries/tree/master/GomoryCut">my GitHub repository</a>.</p>

<h3 id="the-basics">The basics</h3>
<p>Given a Integer Linear Program in the form:</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">(P) \qquad \min \{ cx \mid Ax \leq b, \, x \geq 0, \, x \mbox{ integer} \}</script>

<p>it is possible to rewrite the problem in standard form by adding slack variables:</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">(P) \qquad \min \{ cx \mid Ax + Ix_S = b, \, x \geq 0, \, x \mbox{ integer}, \, x_S \geq 0 \}</script>

<p>where <script type="math/tex">I</script> is the identity matrix and <script type="math/tex">x_S</script> is a vector of slack variables, one for each constraint in <script type="math/tex">(P)</script>.
Let us denote by <script type="math/tex">(\bar{P})</script> the linear relaxation of <script type="math/tex">(P)</script> obtained by relaxing the integrality constraint.</p>

<p>The optimum solution vector of <script type="math/tex">(\bar{P})</script>, if it exists and it is finite, it is used to derive a basis
(for a formal definition of <strong>basis</strong>, see [1] or [3]).
Indeed, the basis partitions the columns of matrix <script type="math/tex">A</script> into two submatrices
<script type="math/tex">B</script> and <script type="math/tex">N</script>, where <script type="math/tex">B</script> is given by the columns corresponding to the basic variables,
and <script type="math/tex">N</script> by columns corresponding to variables out of the base (they are equal to zero in the optimal solution vector).</p>

<p>Remember that, by definition, <script type="math/tex">B</script> is nonsingular and therefore is invertible. 
Using the matrices <script type="math/tex">B</script> and <script type="math/tex">N</script>, it is easy to derive the following inequalities (for details, see any OR textbook, e.g., [1]): </p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{eqnarray}
&Ax = b & \\
&Bx_B + Nx_N = b& \\
&x_B + B^{-1}N\,x_N = B^{-1}\,b & \qquad B \mbox{ is nonsingular} \\
&x_B + \lfloor B^{-1}N \rfloor \,x_N \leq B^{-1}\,b &\qquad  \mbox{since }x \geq 0 \\
&x_B + \lfloor B^{-1}N \rfloor \,x_N \leq \lfloor B^{-1}\,b \rfloor& \qquad x \mbox{ is integer}
\end{eqnarray} %]]&gt;</script>

<p>where the operator <script type="math/tex">\lfloor \cdot \rfloor</script> is applied component wise to the matrix elements.
In practice, for each fractional basic variable, it is possible to generate a valid Gomory cut.</p>

<p>The key step to generate Gomory cuts is to get an optimal basis or, even better, the inverse of the basis matrix <script type="math/tex">B^{-1}</script>
multiplied by <script type="math/tex">A</script> and by <script type="math/tex">b</script>. Once we have that matrix, in order to generate a Gomory cut from a fractional
basic variable, we just use the last equation in the previous derivation, applying it to each row of the system of inequalities</p>

<p>Given the optimal basis, the optimal basic vector is <script type="math/tex">x_B=B^{-1}b</script>, since the non basic variables are equal to zero.
Let <script type="math/tex">j</script> be the index of a fractional basic variable, and let <script type="math/tex">i</script> be the index of the constraint corresponding to
variable <script type="math/tex">j</script> in the equations <script type="math/tex">x_B=B^{-1}A</script>, then the Gomory cut for variable <script type="math/tex">j</script> is:</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">x_j + \sum_{l \in N} \lfloor (B^{-1}N)_{il} \rfloor\,x_l \leq \lfloor (B^{-1}\,b)_i \rfloor</script>

<h3 id="using-the-cplex-callable-library">Using the CPLEX callable library</h3>
<p>The CPLEX callable library (written in C) has the following <em>advanced</em> functions:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://pic.dhe.ibm.com/infocenter/cosinfoc/v12r5/index.jsp?topic=%2Filog.odms.cplex.help%2Frefcallablelibrary%2Fhtml%2Ffunctions%2FCPXbinvarow.html">CPXbinvarow</a> computes the <em>i</em>-th row of the tableau</li>
  <li><a href="http://pic.dhe.ibm.com/infocenter/cosinfoc/v12r5/index.jsp?topic=%2Filog.odms.cplex.help%2Frefcallablelibrary%2Fhtml%2Ffunctions%2FCPXbinvrow.html">CPXbinvrow</a> computes the <em>i</em>-th row of the basis inverse</li>
  <li><a href="http://pic.dhe.ibm.com/infocenter/cosinfoc/v12r5/index.jsp?topic=%2Filog.odms.cplex.help%2Frefcallablelibrary%2Fhtml%2Ffunctions%2FCPXbinvacol.html">CPXbinvacol</a> computes the representation of the <em>j</em>-th column in terms of the basis</li>
  <li><a href="http://pic.dhe.ibm.com/infocenter/cosinfoc/v12r5/index.jsp?topic=%2Filog.odms.cplex.help%2Frefcallablelibrary%2Fhtml%2Ffunctions%2FCPXbinvcol.html">CPXbinvcol</a> computes the <em>j</em>-th column of the basis inverse</li>
</ul>

<p>Using the first two functions, Gomory cuts from an optimal base can be generated as follows:</p>

<p><code>c++ Gomory cut https://github.com/stegua/MyBlogEntries/blob/master/GomoryCut/cpx_gomory.c Fork Me on GitHub
printf("\nGenerate Gomory cuts:\n");
idx = 0;
cut = 0;  /// Index of cut to be added
for ( i = 0; i &lt; m-1; ++i ) 
if ( floor(b_bar[i]) != b_bar[i] ) {
   printf("Row %d gives cut -&gt;   ", i+1);
   POST_CMD( CPXbinvarow(env, model, i, z) );
   rmatbeg[cut] = idx;
   for ( j = 0; j &lt; n1; ++j ) {
      z[j] = floor(z[j]); /// DANGER!
      if ( z[j] != 0 ) {
         rmatind[idx] = j;
         rmatval[idx] = z[j];
         idx++;
      }
      /// Print the cut
      if ( z[j] &gt;= 0 ) printf("+");
      printf("%.1f x%d ", z[j], j+1);
   }
   gc_rhs[cut] = floor(b_bar[i]); /// DANGER!
   gc_sense[cut] = 'L';
   printf("&lt;= %.1f\n", gc_rhs[cut]);
   cut++;
}
/// Add the new cuts
POST_CMD( CPXaddrows (env, model, 0, n_cuts, idx, gc_rhs, gc_sense, 
         rmatbeg, rmatind, rmatval, NULL, NULL) );
</code></p>

<p>The code reads row by row (index <em>i</em>) the inverse basis matrix <script type="math/tex">B^{-1}</script> multiplied by <script type="math/tex">A</script> (line 7),
which is temporally stored in vector <code>z</code>,
and then the code stores the corresponding Gomory cut in the compact matrix given by vectors <code>rmatbeg</code>, <code>rmatind</code>, and <code>rmatval</code> (lines 8-15).
The array <code>b_bar</code> contains the vector <script type="math/tex">B^{-1}b</script> (line 21). In lines 26-27, all the cuts are added at once to the current LP data structure.</p>

<p>On GitHub you find a small program that I wrote to generate Gomory cuts for problems written as <script type="math/tex">(P)</script>.
The repository have an <a href="https://github.com/stegua/MyBlogEntries/blob/master/GomoryCut/README.md">example of execution</a> of my program.</p>

<p>The code is simple only because it is designed for small IPs in the form
<script type="math/tex"> \min\, \{\, cx \mid Ax\, \leq\,b,\, x\geq 0\}</script>.
Otherwise, the code <strong>must</strong> consider the effects of preprocessing, different sense of the constraints,
and additional constraints introduced because of range constraints.</p>

<p>If you are interested in a <strong>real</strong> implementation of <strong>Mixed-Integer Gomory cuts</strong>, 
that are a generalization of Fractional Gomory cuts to <strong>mixed integer linear programs</strong>, 
please look at the <a href="http://scip.zib.de/doc/html/sepa__gomory_8h.shtml">SCIP source code</a>.</p>

<h3 id="additional-readings">Additional readings</h3>
<p>The introduction of Mixed Integer Gomory cuts 
in CPLEX was <strong>The</strong> major breakthrough of CPLEX 6.5 and produced
the version-to-version speed-up given by the blue bars in the chart below
(source: <a href="http://www.ferc.gov/eventcalendar/Files/20100609110044-Bixby,%20Gurobi%20Optimization.pdf">Bixby’s slides available on the web</a>):</p>

<p><img src="http://stegua.github.io/images/cplex65.png"></p>

<p>Gomory cuts are still subject of research, since they pose a number of implementation challenges. 
These cuts suffer from severe numerical issues, mainly because the computation of the inverse matrix
requires the division by its determinant.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“In 1959, […] We started to experience the unpredictability of the computational results rather steadily” (Gomory, see [4]).”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>A recent paper by Cornuejols, Margot, and Nannicini deals with some of these issues [2].</p>

<p>If you like to learn more about how the basis are computed in the CPLEX LP solver, there is very nice paper
by Bixby [3]. The paper explains different approaches to get the first basic feasible solution and
gives some hints of the CPLEX implementation of that time, i.e., 1992. Though the paper does not deal with Gomory
cuts directly, it is a very pleasant reading.</p>

<p>To conclude, for those of you interested in <a href="http://www.math.uiuc.edu/documenta/vol-ismp/vol-ismp.html">Optimization Stories</a>
there is a nice chapter by G. Cornuejols about the <strong>Ongoing Story of Gomory Cuts</strong> [4].</p>

<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<ol>
  <li>
    <p>C.H. Papadimitriou, K. Steiglitz.
<span class="title">Combinatorial Optimization: Algorithms and Complexity</span>. 1998.
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Combinatorial-Optimization-Algorithms-Complexity-Computer/dp/0486402584">[book]</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>G. Cornuejols, F. Margot and G. Nannicini.
<span class="title">On the safety of Gomory cut generators</span>. Submitted in 2012.
<span class="journal">Mathematical Programming Computation, under review.</span> 
<a href="http://faculty.sutd.edu.sg/~nannicini/papers/testing_gomory.pdf">[preprint]</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>R.E. Bixby.
<span class="title">Implementing the Simplex Method: The Initial Basis</span>.
<span class="journal">Journal on Computing</span> vol. 4(3), pages 267--284, 1992.
<a href="http://joc.journal.informs.org/content/4/3/267.short">[abstract]</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>G. Cornuejols.
<span class="title">The Ongoing Story of Gomory Cuts</span>.
<span class="journal">Documenta Mathematica - Optimization Stories.</span> Pages 221-226, 2012.
<a href="http://www.math.uiuc.edu/documenta/vol-ismp/37_cornuejols-gerard.pdf">[preprint]</a></p>
  </li>
</ol>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
